<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://digitalhumanities.unl.edu/resources/schemas/tei/TEIP5.2.0.2/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fern.18561101">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">A City Shower; Awe-ful Thoughts</title>
            <title type="sub">a machine-readable transcription</title>
            <editor xml:id="cm">Carmen McCue</editor>
            <editor xml:id="km">Kevin McMullen</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <date>2014</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">
                  <p>Licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/). Derivatives must be credited to Fanny Fern in The New York Ledger, made available non-commercially, and distributed under the same terms.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="column">
               <analytic>
                  <author ref="#ff">Fanny Fern</author>
                  <title level="a">A City Shower; Awe-ful Thoughts</title>
               </analytic>
               <monogr>
                  <title xml:id="paper" level="j">The New-York Ledger</title>
                  <editor ref="#rb">Robert Bonner</editor>
                  <imprint>
                     <date xml:id="issue_date" when="1856-11-01">1 November 1856</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope type="pp">[4]</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <series>
                  <title level="s">Fresh Fern Leaves</title>
               </series>
            </biblStruct>
            <biblStruct xml:id="issue">
               <monogr>
                  <title level="j" sameAs="#paper"/>
                  <imprint>
                     <date sameAs="#issue_date"/>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <p>This electronic text is a semi-diplomatic transcription of the source text. Hyphenation, punctuation, variant spellings, and errors present in the source text have been retained. The transcription does not attempt to capture all aspects of the original formatting or layout.</p>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="#km" when="2015-09-25">proofed, and further updated encoding</change>
         <change who="#km" when="2014-10-09">updated encoding</change>
         <change who="#cm" when="2012-04-04">transcribed, encoded</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile corresp="#issue">
      <surface xml:id="pp1">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.01.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp2">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.02.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp3">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.03.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp4" type="containsColumn">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.04.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp5">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.05.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp6">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.06.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp7">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.07.jpg"/>
      </surface>
      <surface xml:id="pp8">
         <graphic url="fern18561101.08.jpg"/>
      </surface>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
            
            
            
            
            <div type="column">
                <head type="column">FRESH FERN LEAVES.</head>

                <epigraph>
                    <p>Entered according to Act of Congress, in the year 1856, by ROBERT BONNER, in the Clerk's Office of the District Court for the Southern District of New York.</p>
                </epigraph>

                <head type="main">A CITY SHOWER.</head>

                <p>Patter, patter, patter, down comes a city shower, on dusty and heated pavements; gleefully the willow trees shake out their long, green tresses, and make their toilets in the tiny mirror-pools beneath. The little child runs out, with outspread palm, to catch the cool and pearly drops. The weary laborer, drawing a long, grateful breath, bares the flushed brow of toil; boyhood, with bare and adventurous foot, wades through gutter-rivers, forgetful of birch and bread and butter. Ladies skutter tiptoe, with uplifted skirts, to the shelter of some friendly omnibus; gentlemen, in the independent consciousness of corduroys, take their time and umbrellas, while the poor jaded horses shake their sleek sides, but do not say <hi rend="italic">neigh</hi> to the impromtu shower bath.</p>

                <p>The little sparrows twitter their thanks from the dripping eaves, circling the piazza, then laving their speckled breasts at the tiny lakelets in the spouts. Old Towser lies with his nose to the door-mat sniffing "the cool" with the philosophy of Diogenes. Petrarch sits in the parlor with his Laura, too happy when some vivid lightning flash gives him an excuse for close quarters. Grandpapa puts on his spectacles, walks to the window, and taking a look at the surcharged clouds says, "How this will make the corn grow." The old maid opposite sets out a single geranium, scraggy as herself, invoking some double blossoms. Forlorn experimenter! ever a spinster's affections must centre somewhere.</p>

                <p>See that little pinafore mariner stealing out, with one eye on the nursery window, to navigate his pasteboard boat in the street pools. There's a flash of sunshine! What a glorious rainbow! The little fellow tosses his arms aloft, and gazes at it. Ten to one, the little Yankee, instead of admiring its gorgeous splendor, is wishing he could invert it for a swing, and seizing it at both ends, sweep through the stars. Well, it is nothing new for a child to like "the <hi rend="italic">milky way</hi>."</p>

                <p>Fair weather again! piles of heavy clouds are drifting by, leaving the clear blue sky as serene as when "the morning stars first sang together." Nature's gems sparkle lavishly on glossy leaf, and swaying branch, on bursting bud and flower; while the bow of peace melts gently and imperceptibly away (like a dying saint) into the light of heaven.</p>

                <p>Oh, earth <hi rend="italic">is</hi> gloriously fair! Alas! that the trail of the serpent be over it all!</p>

                <byline>FANNY FERN.</byline>
            </div>
         
         <milestone unit="line"/>

            <div type="column">
                <head type="main">AWE-FUL THOUGHTS.</head>

                <q>"This had from the very beginning of their acquaintance induced in her that <hi rend="italic">awe</hi>, which is the most delicious feeling a wife can have toward a husband."</q>

               <p>"Awe!"&#8212;awe of a man whose whiskers you have trimmed, whose hair you have cut, whose cravats you have tied, whose shirts you have "put into the wash," whose boots and shoes you have kicked into the closet, whose dressing-gown you have worn while combing your hair; who has been down cellar with you at eleven o'clock at night, to hunt for a chicken-bone; who has hooked your dresses, unlaced your boots, fastened your bracelets, and tied on your bonnet; who has stood before your looking-glass, with thumb and finger on his proboscis, scraping his chin; whom you have buttered, and sugared, and toasted, and tea-ed; whom you have seen asleep with his mouth wide open!&#8212;&#8212;Ri&#8212;diculous!</p>

                <byline>FANNY FERN.</byline>
            </div>
            
            
            
            
            
        </body>
   </text>
</TEI>